Finding Aid for the Nina Byers papers, 1946-2006 LSC.1898
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nina Byers papers
1946-2006
bulk 1965-2006
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.1898
2.4 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Nina Byers was a theoretical physicist and professor in UCLA's Department of Physics and Astronomy. She joined UCLA in 1961 as an assistant professor, working on particle physics, CP-violation, and pion-nuclear charge-exchange scattering. Byers retired in 1993. This collection consists of materials related to her teaching career, research and personal life. The papers include materials related to courses she taught, seminar notes, research, anti-nuclear proliferation materials, professional and personal correspondence, and photographs. Additionally included are materials related to the publication of her book Out of the Shadows: Contributions of Twentieth-Century Women to Physics (2006).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Morissa Landinsky Cohen; gift; 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9982861973606533
Biography/History
Nina Byers was a theoretical physicist and professor in UCLA's Department of Physics and Astronomy. She was born in January 19, 1930 in Los Angeles, CA, and graduated from UC Berkeley with a BA in physics in 1950. She received her PhD from the University of Chicago in 1956. Byers did postdoctoral work at the University of Birmingham, England, followed by a research position at Stanford University in 1958. She then began her teaching career at UCLA in 1961 as an assistant professor, working on particle physics, CP-violation, and pion-nuclear charge-exchange scattering. Byers was the only female professor in UCLA's Physics and Astronomy Department for more than 20 years.
Throughout the late 1960s and 1970s Byers split her time between teaching at UCLA and Oxford University. During this period, Byers was politically active, participating in efforts to support affirmative action for women in the UC system and advocating against nuclear proliferation. She supported awareness and education regarding the Holocaust. Byers also opposed the requirement that university faculty take loyalty oaths, which led to her decision to work in England for some time in the late 1950s.
In the 1980s she was an active member of the American Physical Society. Retiring in 1993, Byers remained an active professor emeritus. Her experience as a female physicist was central to her commitment to increase the representation of women in the sciences, particularly physics. Her work to document the accomplishments of women in this field culminated in her book Out of the Shadows: Contributions of Twentieth Century Women to Physics (2006). She also led an initiative to develop a website documenting women in the field of physics, Contributions to 20th Century Women to Physics. Byers passed away on June 5, 2014.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of materials related to the teaching career, research, and personal life of UCLA Physics Professor Emerita Nina Byers. The papers includes materials related to courses she taught, lecture and seminar notes, research, anti-nuclear proliferation materials, and a university study in which she participated. Additionally there is professional and personal correspondence, and photographs, including letters regarding the 1965 Watts Riots, affirmative action for women in the UC system, and loyalty oaths. Materials related to Byers' personal life and education include her physics qualifying exams, datebook, curriculum vitae and biographical materials, and correspondence regarding her book Out of the Shadows: Contributions of Twentieth Century Women to Physics (2006).
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Academic files, 1968-2005
Series 2: Correspondence and photographs, 1946-2006
Series 3: Personal files, 1951-2005
Original order of materials has been maintained.
Related Material
Contributions of 20th Century Women to Physics: Records of the UCLA Website (Collection 458) Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Women physicists -- United States -- Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Physics--Faculty -- Archives
- Series 1: Academic files, 1968-2005
  Scope and Content
  The series includes materials related to Byers' activities as a professor at UCLA, including instructional materials for physics and gender studies courses, lecture notes for a talk on the Holocaust, course outlines, exams and problem sets, anti-war and anti-nuclear materials, and a university study in which she participated.
  - Courses: Physics C185, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Courses: Physics C185, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Courses: Physics 226B and 226C, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Courses: Physics 226A, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Courses: Physics 226A and 226B, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Courses: Physics 224, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proton decay notes and research, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Courses: Women's Studies M135/History M198G, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Holocaust lecture and notes, 1997-2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Course materials and notes, circa 2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Exams and course materials, 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Oxford course materials, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Seminars and lectures, 1969-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Papers and articles, 1958-2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gender studies materials, 1995-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - History of science materials, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Anti-nuclear materials, 1981-2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Contributions of 20th Century Women to Physics (CWP), 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - American Physical Society, 1995-2003 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Forum on History of Physics, 1982-2004 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks, 1958-1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - University Transition Study, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Correspondence and photographs, 1946-2006
  The series includes professional and personal correspondence and photos, including letters discussing the Watts Riots in 1965, affirmative action in regards to women in the UC system, and correspondence with a potential employer from 1955-1956 regarding her refusal to take a loyalty oath. Photographs are personal snapshots with unidentified persons and dates are limited to 1946-1958 and 1991-2006. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1946-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1948-1958 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Correspondence: Loyalty oath, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Watts Riots, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Association of Academic Women (AAW), 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence with Xavier Carelse, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1991-1999 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 2000-2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Series 3: Personal files, 1951-2005
  The series includes subject material reflecting Byers' personal life, including her physics qualifying exams as a student, datebooks, curriculum vitae, biographical materials, research on Austrian-Swedish physicist Lisa Meitner, correspondence regarding the great-granddaughter of Peter Carl, Fabergé, Tatiana Fabergé, and research, notes and correspondence related to her book Out of the Shadows: Contributions of Twentieth Century Women to Physics.
  - Physics qualifying exams, circa 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Calendar and personal documents, 1967-1974 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lisa Meitner notes, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Out of the Shadows book materials, 1999-2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum vitae and biographical materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Eulogies, 1995-2001 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tatiana Fabergé, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)